it is the start of the holiday season
which means we are on a permanent bulk
welcome to strength weekly the weekly
show that brings you everything you need
to know from around the barbell
game I'm David Thomas to I'm joined by
Phil bman today we're talking about thlb
dead lft for reps barbon's latest
acquisition we are a
businessman as well as some other
important things on the docket but
before we get to that make sure you
subscribe to barbend on
YouTube
[Music]
Phil how are you feeling today and what
is your favorite Thanksgiving dish I'm
ready to talk about some uh heavy
deadlifts and uh my favorite dish
obviously has to be sweet potatoes
covered in marshmallows give me the
calories let me get all this bulking
going on I love me those side dishes
Phil I am disappointed because while
that is great in a variety of
carbohydrates it is low in Pro protein
what are you doing with your life oh
come on you know you know we got to we
got to scoop some of that way in in
those in that stuffing what are you what
what does your Thanksgiving look like
I'm actually G to throw this out there
vanilla wayy protein
in sweet potato casserole or like on
sweet P that actually could be pretty
good and creamy you know what I mean i'
I'd eat it I I we we should do a chef
reactions to that 10 out of 10 I'd eat
put some vanilla away in uh in your
sweet potatoes it might be terrible it
might not couldn't tell you
all right first up today Jamal Browner
deadlifting a thousand plus pounds for
four RS Phil if you wouldn't mind uh
take us through this lift and then we
will compare it to uh very few
historical precedents this is not the
first time we've seen him deadlift a
th000 pounds uh we've seen him do it
multiple times before this is the first
time that he's done it for four reps uh
which is why it's quite notable uh he
also recently competed for the first
time in strongman so the dance between
is he a strongman is he a powerlifter in
my view he's still very much a
powerlifter he still trains very much as
a powerlifter but he was so good at
deadlifting that literally he was
invited to compete at the world deadlift
championships with a bunch of strong men
because they saw how good he was in the
deadlift on his social like you can go
to his deadlifts on his Instagram and
see strongman being like tagging giants
live and being like should this guy
deadlift at the world deadlift
championships like maybe he should get
an invite to the world deadlift
championships and he did and then he
competed as a strongman for a little bit
so we asked around for all the
knowledgeable Folks at barbend and this
th2 lb quadruple really only has
historical precedence in two different
lifts one Chris duffins 1,2 lb double
deadlift nearly triple that he did with
straps and in a Sumo stance and then
Kristoff Wass bicki actually did triple
1,6 pounds against Sumo and uh wh straps
but really only three people that we
know of recorded on video have taken
over a thousand pounds for multiple refs
in the deadlift Phil of Browner Duffin
and whis bicki uh which do you think
stands out is the most impressive to you
well you can't discount wh bicky's like
heaviest ever I mean it's the heaviest
ever I mean it's in training but it's
the heaviest ever I think Browner
browner's just been really impressive
for a really really long time so the
fact that he's like dabbled in both
conventional and Sumo and we've seen him
be able to deadlift extremely heavy and
both also is pretty impressive and as
you said all all of these deadlifts that
are th000 PBS uh Plus have been with
straps so they they were not done raw
which you would need to do if you were
competing in a raw competition uh but
really impressive nonetheless we saw at
the world deadlift championships in uh
Jolly Old England he did 430 kilograms
conventional now I'm interested to see
if he were to train specifically for the
world deadlift championships what he
could actually show up and do and if he
could push you know close to that 500
kilo Mark with more specific training
what other things should we keep in mind
when comparing powerlifting style
deadlifting comparing that to strongman
style deadlift competitions a couple of
notable differences in strongman you're
always typically allowed to wear a suit
which would be considered equip lifting
you can always use straps but you must
lift conventional there is no such thing
as Sumo deadlifting in strongman that
doesn't exist another notable difference
though is in strongman you are allowed
to Hitch the barbell if you can get the
bar locked out off the floor doesn't
matter how you get there conventional
stance get it up that's it in
powerlifting you call whatever your
weight is on the barbell and you get
three attempts and you choose what
weight is going to go on the barbell and
you're competing against yourself in
strongman you lift in rounds it is
dedicated weights that each athlete has
to like lock out and secure and so you
could go into you know seven rounds of
of deadlifting incrementally increasing
that weight all the way and so you know
your top lift of let's say somebody
actually was able to contend with 500
kilos if like that's the case but it was
on rep seven it's like okay well your
nervous system just took six reps of
extremely heavy weight up until that
point which would be a lot more load
than what you would see in a
powerlifting competition granted they've
al already squatted in bench press by
the time that they deadlift so maybe
there's some comparison there but in
strongman deadlift you go until you're
if you're hitting Max the rounds just
keep going until they can't go anymore
and somebody wins well we will
transition quickly into the next story
of the day look at barbend we normally
report on the news and sometimes very
occasionally very rarely we actually
make the news or at least we're calling
this news because guess what barbend has
acquired morning chock up morning shock
up being the premier coverage outlet for
functional fitness and Crossfit both on
their website their social channels and
Via their very popular newsletter
they've been around since 2016 and guess
what they're part of barbend now we
acquire them this is Joe jenon Pala a
managing editor of the morning chalkup
we are very excited to be joining the
barbend and pillar for news team I speak
for the home morning shock up crew when
I say that we are amped for the
opportunities that this new partnership
is going to afford US barbend and pillar
4 have made it their mission to be at
the center of coverage of all things
strength and strength sports related and
morning Chu up is going to play a key
role in bolstering that mission what I
want to get out of the way is that not
much is going to change about MCU if you
get their newsletter look I'm biased I
SED barbend right I did this because I
wanted more coverage for strength Sports
and I believe in Barb Ben's continued
Mission so you've been covering the
strength game for a while including
CrossFit um you know what does this
acquisition signal for you as far as how
we as an organization are going to cover
that sport that realm of Fitness I mean
I think high tide raises all boats you
know the the combinate the combining of
the minds uh a two Elite uh coverage
outlets for CrossFit is only going to
make the CrossFit coverage better and we
know we talked about in the last episode
uh how there are changes going into the
2024 season so it's actually a pretty
ripe time for this acquisition to happen
because as there are some big changes in
CrossFit there will be some changes in
CrossFit coverage but it's all for the
better so I do want to quote Barb Ben
senior editor Jay seraphino who will be
doing a lot of the good work integrating
barbin and morning shock up and actually
building out expanded morning shock up
coverage here's what Jay sarapo says the
main thing is that we want to continue
putting out the content that fans love
from MCU it's morning shock up little
acronym for you so they'll get the same
high quality competition analysis and
unique stories from the community as
always but we're also looking to
revitalize the subscription content and
we exploring exciting partnership
opportunities across brands with
different content creators MCU laid a
great Foundation over the years the next
step is to keep building upon it and
exciting New Opportunities and
initiatives we're going to continue with
what Morning chak has been producing but
add new lenses to see CrossFit and to to
see this community both on the
competitive and non-competitive side
which makes me really excited all right
Phil but enough about CrossFit let's go
back to powerlifting cuz we have a 57
kogam woman back squatting
227.50 kilograms that's just over that
glorious beautiful 500 pound Mark that's
uh Kenia monserat did that at the ipf
equipped World Championships in the
world of powerlifting a record that
stood for four or more years or even
five years in this case is a bit of a
rarity especially because of the sports
growth how many great lifters are really
pushing the envelope there so this is
one we've been looking at for a while if
you look at the record tables like
2018 that's old in this game uh Phil
what do you think about this squad if
you look at all the federations this is
an ipf equipped world record uh which
means that the ipf sanctioned it so any
event that the ipf sanctions is where
this record would be contested or where
it would count monzer has been in the
game for a long time I mean like looking
at her her resume since she was in her
teenage years however despite breaking
the world record she did not land at the
top of the podium she has uh yet to win
the ipf World Championships although
she's competed multiple times she has
not actually won that title yet despite
breaking the world record here but she
has won on the world stage many a time
she's won at the Pan-American
championships the fact that she broke
this record obviously notable it's a
world record lift and uh I think now
it's just if and when she is going to
actually win a world title it feels like
an inevitability as it does often the
case when somebody cracks a world record
and isn't only a specialist in that lift
she's a well-rounded lifter and I expect
more from her going forward she is a top
lifter at the Pan-American chip
championships every year like expected
to gold at the Pan-American champ
championships so yes tip of the hat to
Ecuador well done uh you have a champion
powerlifter all right let's move on
because one thing we want to ask this
isn't so much a news story this is just
fun who's the strongest Mr Olympia
winner Dr Conor heffernon who is one of
the world's Premier strength historians
if not the Premier strength historian he
wrote an article a little while back
that we wanted to highlight on barbin
who's the strongest Mr Olympia and he
broke down 10 different Mr Olympia
winners and compare them Yeah we
actually have two potential winners for
who the strongest Mr Olympia is so this
isn't one of those like clickbaity
articles where you ask a question and
there's no answer because he came with
receipts that's the best part about this
so not only is this like a calibrated
class to the people who have won the
Olympia but it's also a calibrated class
of the Mr Olympia champions who are like
I'm lifting two max out in my training
that we can actually pull receipts from
so it becomes even more narrow of that
class because not only is it the
athletes that are the strongest but also
we're like I'm gonna be the
strongest yeah I gotta be honest
backstage at the Olympia the athletes
aren't asking each other how much you
bench right they're asking about body
fat percentage they're asking about
symmetry that's what they're focused on
right this is not this is a this is a
physique sport it is an aesthetic sport
on this topic one of the I think
simplest and most ideal quotes for this
type of uh discussion is one from the
2023 world Strongest Man Mitchell Hooper
who when asked about what is the
difference between something like strong
man or powerlifting versus bodybuilding
body lifting trains muscles strong man
and powerlifting trains
movements you are looking to be
aesthetic on stage as a bodybuilder if
you have a really good Flawless
technique in your deadlift if that's not
actually helping you develop the muscles
to look good on stage it's not your goal
so this is like very very specific to
these athletes of going not only am I
lifting heavy but I'm doing it in a way
that might be different from how
somebody might max out if they were
training for a powerlifting competition
or Strongman Competition we got to start
with Ronnie Coleman King Ronnie eight
time Mr Olympia winner eight time
consecutively just want to point out
Ronnie Coleman this man showed up
conditioned at about 300 pounds on stage
and he is not that tall but he is W was
wide as a house Big Ronnie Coleman yeah
buddy lightweight ain't nothing but a
peanut ain't no one want to lift these
heavy ass weights but I'll lift the
weights Ronnie Coleman out of Texas back
squatting 800 pounds for a double
deadlifting 800 pounds for a double
those videos are
legendary what I think is interesting
about Coleman's training it's a bit
unlike basically anyone else at the top
realm of bodybuilding he was lifting
equipped you see his world famous and
there's like a whole generation of
people who are brought up on these
videos on YouTube I I am among this
generation you this back squat 800 pound
back squat double he's doing it with a
squat suit right like most bodybuilders
are not even thinking yeah I need to put
on a squat suit because they're training
the muscles they're not training the
movement right but here Ronnie is he's
like I'm Gonna Get The Best of Both
Worlds here and for him it worked for
him this incredibly heavy overloading
stimulus it did work and it helped him
craft what someone would argue is the
greatest physique of all time I would
argue that Ronnie also has the most
famous lifts never done because anytime
he's ever been interviewed about this
lift he's always like had more in the
tank could have done another like he's
he it still it haunts him to this day
that he didn't like get another one it's
just remarkable stuff and it coincided
with like the early days of YouTube and
the early days of video verality and
it's just a perfect storm and Ronnie is
just such such a showman right like R
Ronnie Coleman is a man born to be a
bodybuilder right not only for his
physique and his his work ethic and his
dedication that to that lifestyle as
difficult as it is and it certainly took
a toll and he's the first to admit that
but his personality is is effervescent
and you can't help but not like Ro like
I've never met anyone whether they've
met him in person or just followed him
through his career and after I've never
met anyone who's like I don't like
Ronnie Coleman okay I got to move on
we're going to talk about uh Franco
Columbu who really was a stall of a
golden age of bodybuilding Arnold torer
training partner and best friend now
Franco passed away a few years ago
Franco is truly one of the most famous
and most successful crossover strength
athletes we've seen here are some of his
reported uh Max lifts a 655 pound squat
525 pound bench and 750b deadlift and
one that thing that's really funny about
him is if you watch Pumping Iron back in
the day everyone refers to him as the
strongest bodybuilder at the time he was
also like the smallest guy on stage
as far as sture but they refer to him as
the strongest bodybuilder right they're
like oh yeah Franco can lift the most
and there's even a video of him lifting
a car to move it in his Italian Hometown
in Sardinia like there's a there's a
there's a clip in that movie of him like
lifting the fender of a car to get a car
out of the way right dude was massively
strong and spoiler alert pound-for-pound
almost certainly the strongest Mr
Olympia Champion we've ever seen if you
were to go and look at what world
records look like in the powerlifting
space for any division most of those
world records are somewhere in the in
the three times an athletes body weight
in that category lift if you get into
the four times your body weight lift
that is a very very unique and small
class of athletes that can pull that and
if he weighed between 185 and 200 pounds
when he did his 750 pound deadlift that
is more that is a three and a half X
lift a three and a half times body
weight conventional deadlift that is at
a World Elite level you know I mean
these numbers are eye popping for an
athlete who weighed probably about 200
Max 200 pounds on stage just absolutely
eye popping I want to highlight one more
and again please read this article this
article's great and it goes into
in-depth on the training style and
capabilities of of of some legendary
lifters
Phil we we're highlighting three let's
highlight someone who's a little more
contemporary you mind taking this one
away because I know he's one of your
favorite athletes to cover
yeah 2022 Mr Olympia hotti shupin uh he
can rep 675 pounds on the squat uh which
is supremely heavy uh he can get up to
705 pounds for a double in the deadlift
I mean if you if we know hottie he is
not the the the largest guy on stage but
he's always the most conditioned his his
muscle maturity and the graininess of of
his physique is always Second To None he
looks like that at his conditioning
level and then he can also lift this
heavy I mean the guy can hit 440 lbs for
five reps in the bench press I mean this
dude is immensely strong and that does
not hinder his Aesthetics in any way it
seems to only benefit it we have Ronnie
Coleman as like you know he is the the
Paramount in this space and I always
think about it the same way where it's
like the LeBron versus uh Jordan debate
and it's like if LeBron came first then
nobody would be talking about this
debate at all but Jordan came first so
like how can it not be Jordan if it was
if hottie came first like maybe we're
just talking about hottie the way that
we talk about Coleman you know what I
mean it's like he's that strong he's
that strong love it well spoiler alert
you should read the article but Ronnie's
the strongest Franco's the strongest
pound-for-pound H but hottie some
impressive stuff for a person who's
known more for his Symmetry and
conditioning than anything else and a
true recent Champion uh and one of the
bodybuilders who's always in the
conversation today for the Mr Olympia
title well sadly Phil or maybe
fortunately for folks who are sick of us
that brings us to the end of strength
weekly but we'll be back with more in
the coming weeks
enjoy your Thanksgiving folks remember
it's bulking season and no one can tell
you otherwise until then I'm David
Thomas tow I'm Phil Blackman with
bar.com enjoy your marshmallow covered
sweet potatoes
[Music]
everybody